Mieczyslaw Kierklo papers 1940-2004 CPAA 87-47
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
Mieczyslaw Kierklo papers
1940-2004
Kierklo, Mieczyslaw
CPAA 86-02
2 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Mr. Mieczyslaw [Michael] Kierklo was born in Poland. He attended school and work there until the outbreak of WWII. In 1940 he was arrested by Russians and sent to Workuta, a labor camp. In 1942, after he was freed, he joined the newly established Polish Army in the USSR and left Russia with General Andres, and fought with them until the end of the war. In 1954 he immigrated to the US and established his life in Connecticut. He became very involved with various Polish and Polish American organizations. Soon his writing talent was used for various occasions. He wrote to publication called "Weteran" about his war experience and wrote about Polonia activities and events to the Polish daily Nowy Dziennik. For numerous occasions he wrote short poems to celebrate the live and activities of an organization or individual.
Historical/Biographical Note
Mieczyslaw Kierklo (May 18, 1919 - March 23, 2004). Mr. Kierklo was born in Poland in 1919, and worked in the aircraft industry in Rzeszow before the WWII. During the war he participated in the underground resistance movement and was arrested in 1940. Later, he was sent to labor camp in Workuta. After the Sikorski-Stalin pact to create the Polish Army in the USSR, he was released from Workuta and left Russia with General Anders army in 1942. During the war he fought with the First Polish Armoured Division under General Maczek.
Mr. Kierklo immigrated to the US in 1954 and lived in Newington, CT. He was active in Polish veteran's organizations, and the Polish American Congress. He was also active parishioner of the Holy Cross church and the Polonia Paderewski choir in New Britain, CT. He financially supported many domestic and international human rights organizations. Mr. Kierklo was very involved in the celebration of Poland's Millennium of Christianity in 1966. He was a writer and a poet, and he published several books of his poetry. Together with Mr. Jan Wojcik, they published "Polonia in Connecticut". He was regularly published in many Polish and Polish American magazines and newspapers. Mr. Kierklo wrote numerous short poems and limericks for various occasions, including anniversaries, birthdays, name days and other family celebrations.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection consists of Mr. Kierklo memoirs published in the Polish language magazine, Weteran, and numerous articles from local Polish and Polish American newspapers. In addition, books written or co-written by Mr. Kierklo and anniversary pamphlet publications, are included. Correspondence and bulletins of local organizations and information about various political and cultural Polish American events are in the collection also.
The collection is open for research.
Material in the collection was donated by Mr. Kierklo in 1987, and then again in 1992.
Search Terms
Mieczyslaw Kierklo; Stowarzyszenie Weteranów Armii Polskiej w Ameryce.; Placówka 111 im. Gen. Hallera (New Britain, Conn.).; Sacred Heart of Jesus Church (New Britain, Conn.).; Holy Cross Church (New Britain, Conn.).; Polish Americans -- Connecticut.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- New Britain.; Correspondence.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Clippings.
Related Material
For related material see the following collections:
Jan Wojcik papers CPAA 05-14
Czeslaw Gieniewski papers CPAA 08-09
Arrangement
Material in the collection is arranged by date.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Mieczyslaw Kierklo - biography and obituary., 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Dluga Droga: wspomnienia z lat 1940-1947", memoirs of mr. kierklo published in magazine Weteran, in Polish., 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Russian Red Cross response to Michael Kierklo inquiry related to his imprisonment during WWII., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
- Correspondence in Polish., 1967-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence in English., 1967-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Chor Polonia im. Paderewskiego - correspondence., 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Polish Singer Alliance, District 7, 27th Convention, New Britain., May, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Polish Army Veterans in America - mandate for Mr. Kierklo to participate in National Conventions., 1965, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Holy Cross Pageant - play for 35th anniversary, Polish and English translation., November, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Commemoration Days and Proclamations for various patriotic events., 1969-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Aid to the Polish workers from Connecticut State AFLO-CIO., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Various announcements., 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Ronald Reagan address to the Centennial meeting of the Knights of Columbus, Hartford., August 3, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Polish American Congress (PAC) District of Connecticut - bulletin., March, April 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Anniversary booklets and various programs., 1973, 1976, 1981, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Newspaper articles and clippings related to Polonia., 1937, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Rymowane Sciezki" by Michael Kierklo., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Pamietniki/Souvenir Books, bounded, include Mr. Kierklo poems., 1967-1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Souvenir Books/Jednodniowki, bounded, include Mr. Kierklo poems., 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Listy, artykuly, reportaze, kronika., 1966-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Listy, artykuly, reportaze, kronika., 1975-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Listy artykuly, reportaze, kronika., 1975-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Listy, artykuly, reportaze, kronika., 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Listy, artykuly, reportaze, kronika., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Listy, artykuly, reportaze, kronika., 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Listy, artykuly, reportaze, kronika., 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)